Guide to the Rice University KTRU Radio records, 1962-2018 UA 011
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University KTRU Radio records
1962-2018
1962-1988
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 011
27 Linear Feet (27 boxes)
2.57 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_001 (2.57GB)
0.948 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_002 (0.948 GB)
0.78 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_003 (0.78 GB)
3.42 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_004 (3.42 GB)
2.91 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_005 (2.91 GB)
6.58 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_006 (6.58 GB)
8.75 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_007 (8.75 GB)
13.9 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_008 (13.9 GB)
2.69 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_009 (2.69 GB)
6.23 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_010 (6.23 GB)
2.51 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_011 (2.51 GB)
4.08 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_012 (4.08 GB)
8.08 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_013 (8.08 GB)
3.17 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_014 (3.17 GB)
5.30 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_015 (5.30 GB)
5.23 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_016 (5.23 GB)
5.05 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_017 (5.05 GB)
12.40 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_018 (12.40 GB)
7.27 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_019 (7.27 GB)
3.68 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_020 (3.68 GB)
1.23 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_021 (1.23 GB)
1.00 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_022 (1.00 GB)
0.765 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_023 (0.765 GB)
0.612 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_024 (0.612 GB)
2.30 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_025 (2.30 GB)
9.36 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_026 (9.36 GB)
4.44 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_027 (4.44 GB)
2.95 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_028 (2.95 GB)
2.73 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_029 (2.73 GB)
1.70 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_030 (1.70 GB)
1.90 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_031 (1.90 GB)
4.01 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_032 (4.01 GB)
0.165 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_033 (0.165 GB)
0.875 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_034 (0.875 GB)
1.97 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_035 (1.97 GB)
1.33 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_036 (1.33 GB)
1.89 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_037 (1.97 GB)
1.46 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_038 (1.46 GB)
0.0683 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0011aip_039 (0.0683 GB)
Audio recordings and administrative files reflecting the daily business of the KTRU Radio station at Rice University. Recordings include newscasts, interviews with rock, jazz and classical musicians, Rice Presidents' State of the University speeches and recorded live music. Administrative records include radio directors' meeting minutes, "Gripes and Groans" books from the DJ booth, programming notes, election forms, DJ handbook, licensing information, and correspondence. Date range: 1962-2012 Quantity: 13.5 linear feet (27 boxes)
Biographical / Historical
KTRU began in February 1967 as a two-watt station, KHCR, broadcast by students from Hanzsen College in the Hanzsen basement. In 1968 the station relocated to the basement of the Rice Memorial Center and broadcast throughout campus on 580 AM as KOWL. During the process of licensing and transitioning to FM, students discovered that the call letters KOWL were already in use by a station in California and in 1969 the station was renamed KTRU, for The Rice University. In 1970 the FM committee was established as a guiding entity of the licensing process and an application was submitted to the FCC. When the license request was granted in 1971, KTRU's power upgraded to 10 watts and the station began broadcasting at 91.7 FM from the top of Sid Richardson College, reaching approximately an 8 mile radius of campus. At this stage, KTRU, frequently referred to as "the radio", identified itself primarily as a source of diverse and underexposed music while incorporating campus news and events of interests to emphasize the educational purposes of the service. The staff was entirely volunteer, comprised mainly of electrical engineering majors due to the technical complexities of the equipment. KTRU evolved from 250 watts in 1974 to 650 watts in 1980, followed by an unexpected leap to 50,000 watts in 1991. This major shift emerged from the ambitions of neighboring station KRTS 92.1 whose request to expand to 50,000 was denied by the FCC due to the complete overpowering of KTRU's broadcast that would result. KRTS reached an agreement with Rice administrators to pay for the installation and maintenance of the new transmitter, located off campus in Humble, a northwest suburb of Houston. One consequence of the move was the interference of the Texas Medical Center with the broadcast signal, causing poor reception on campus and a decrease in the student audience. In 1997 a committee was formed to redirect KTRU in terms of a "university asset". The tensions between KTRU staff and the university administration manifested in November 2000 when two DJ's protested an arrangement made to broadcast more athletic events by playing punk rock songs over the last half of a Rice women's basketball game. The station was abruptly shut down by administrators for nine days until reopened after a series of protests condemning the university's action and negotiations with the station.
KTRU's content progressed from art rock in the 1970s to alternative, experimental, and underground rock in the 1980s, mirroring the national musical movement of the time. This decade also brought forth the addition of specialty shows, which balanced the alternative bent with segments of jazz, blues, folk, classical, independent and world music. Most recently KTRU boasts a similar eclectic mix of tunes directed away from the mainstream and towards open-minded tastes. Additionally, KTRU broadcasts Rice athletic events, interviews, public lectures of Rice affiliates, concerts from the Shepherd School of Music, and news and events relating to the campus and beyond.
Up until 2010, KTRU broadcasted twenty-four hours a day from a 50,000 watt antenna and streamed online from the Ley Student Center at Rice University. As of April 28, 2011, KTRU no longer broadcasted on the 91.7 frequency, which had been sold to the University of Houston. It only streamed music online until KPFT allowed KTRU to broadcast on its HD2 channel.
For more information, visit KTRU on-line at http://74.53.234.138/.
Scope and Contents
Audio recordings and administrative files reflecting the daily business of the KTRU Radio station at Rice University. Recordings include newscasts, interviews with rock, jazz and classical musicians, Rice Presidents' State of the University speeches and recorded live music. Administrative records include radio directors' meeting minutes, "Gripes and Groans" books from the DJ booth, programming notes, election forms, DJ handbook, licensing information, and correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was transferred to the Woodson Research Center in 1988 by David Stivers and Tony Rossini.
Accruals
More material may be added to this collection.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Music
Document Types
letters (correspondence); agendas (administrative records); audiotapes
- Series I: Audio recordings, 1968-2007, 59004
  - Sub-Series: 1968/1969
    - Masterson Mass Student Meeting, 1969-02; wrc06203; 59013 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Contents include: A student meeting taking place within the Physics Amphitheater. Students who participated on the Advisory Committee to select the next president of Rice University talk about what they were told by administration, what they saw during the meetings, and what the administration did. This student meeting took place soon after the announcement of Dr. William Masterson as the new university president. Speakers: Bari Kaplan, Barry Kaplan, Warren Skaaren
    - William Masterson addressing students, 1969-02-00; wrc07891 (Box 1)
      Contents include: (00:01) Dr. William Masterson addressing students and faculty via a bullhorn during the Masterson Crisis. He also takes questions and statements from the crowd; (12:12) KOWL DJ interviews Dr. Clark Read about the crisis and the public media; (16:17) A phone conversation about meeting with the media. Speakers: William Masterson, Jean Claude De Braemaker, Clark Read, Warren Skaaren
    - Masterson Crisis phone interviews, 1969-02-00; wrc07580 (Box 1)
      Contents include: KOWL DJ interviews various people about their opinions regarding the Board of Trustees selecting Dr. William Masterson as University President. Speakers: Paul Pfeiffer, Warren Skaaren, Lon Del Rio, John Worrell
    - Masterson Crisis phone interviews, 1969-02-00; wrc07892 (Box 1)
      Contents include: KOWL DJ interviews Dr. Wilfred S. Dowden on the American Association of University Professors reaction to the Masterson Crisis, as well as his views on the crisis. Speakers: Wilfred S. Dowden
    - Masterson Crisis interview, 1969-02-00; wrc07893 (Box 1)
      Contents include: Bill Thomas and John Sorti interview Dr. Donald Clayton, Dr. Clark Read, Dr. David Nissen, Dr. Lee Rudee, and Christopher "Turque" Tomlinson about the Masterson Crisis. Because of the age of the reel, the recording has a few technical problems. The recording ends abruptly. Speakers: Bill Thomas, John Sorti, Donald Clayton, Clark Read, David Nissen, Lee Rudee, Christopher "Turque" Tomlinson
    - Reports and meetings on the Charles Freeman case, 1969-04-12; wrc06204; 59016 (Box 1)
      Contents include: (00:01) Student Association and faculty meeting pertaining to the case of Charles Freeman, the first African American student at Rice University; (08:33) News report on Charles Freeman case; (12:05) Student Senate statement on meeting; (13:35) Official press release from the Student Association read by Jeff Cox about Frank Vandiver's decision to not readmit Charles Freeman. Since more than one track was recorded at the same time, this audio has been altered and extraneous audio has been deleted. Speakers: Stewart West, Lon del Rio, Bennet Falk, Mike McKinley, Jim Gregory, Jeff Cox, John Sorte
  - Sub-Series: 1969/1970
    All of the items in this year have been digitized. Those items that are online are located at: https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/96594
    For all nearline items, there are master file wavs and access copy mp3s. Nearline items include audio files containing copyrighted information or are not suitable for online access.
    - News Master A, 1969-09 - 1969-10; wrc06205; 59014 (Box 1)
      Contents include: (00:00) The Incredible String Band review; (1:08) Charles Freeman clarifications on his status as the first African-American student at Rice; (03:40) Baker College's Grungy Panties movie review; (05:52) Interviews for Student Association committees; (07:03) Rice Owls football game vs VMI; (08:54) Jim Morrison exclamation from The Soft Parade album; (09:17) Section of "The Last Trip to Tulsa" by Neil Young; (11:04) Hello Hamlet review; (11:56) Hello Hamlet; (12:50) Possible university and college drug policies; (14:54) Baker College meeting on possible university drug policy; (16:03) Rice Owls football starting line-up; (16:47) Section from a parody of "Banana Boat Song" (17:08) Water balloon war; (18:07) Astro militia protest commentary; (19:02) Astro militia march comment; (20:18) Rice Owls football vs. LSU after party preview; (21:07) Coach Bo Hagan on Rice Owls football; (23:18) Water wars between the colleges; (24:39) Rice Owls football vs. LSU; (27:31) Campanile 1969 yearbook announcement; (28:18) Problem over nudity between publishers and editors of the Campanile; (29:37) Campanile editor Gary Grether on TV show "News on Campus"; (30:21) Medal of Honor protest; (31:38) Vietnam War Moratorium Day; (32:51) Events on Vietnam War Moratorium Day; (35:59) Art exhibit "Reflections on War"; (36:46) Vigil for Rice war dead at Will Rice statue. Speakers: Mark Fowler, Bill Thomas, John Doerr, Bill Cavnar, Pat Baum, Carl Bear, Bo Hagan, Dick Fuqua, Austin Bay, Mark Sivers, Bill Haymes, Allen Matusow
    - News Master B, 1969-10 - 1969-11; wrc06206; 59015 (Box 1)
      Contents include: (00:29) Vigil for Rice war dead at William M. Rice statue; (02:42) Rededication to peace; (03:39) Dr. Allen Matusow seminar: (04:44) Rice University moratorium news; (06:08) Art exhibit "Reflections on War"; (6:40) Vigil for Rice war dead at William M. Rice statue; (07:09) Physical changes to Rice during moratorium day; (07:50) Moratorium days at colleges in Texas; (08:23) End of Dr. Allen Matusow seminar; (09:45) Speaking on the national moratorium; (12:36) KTRU News promo; (13:36) Rice Owls Footbal preview before SMU game; (14:43) Roger Priest and charges against him; (15:48) Jerry Jeff Walker, Guy Clark, and John Carrick perform at RMC; (17:23) Contesting of the Freshman election by the SA; (19:23) Comments on SA Election, (20:45) Dan Rather's visit; (22:08) Rumor on naming of new Rice president; (23:20) Freshman Football review University of Texas game; (24:15) Oleo Strut coffeehouse representatives going to Will Rice College; (25:30) SA contested election; (26:29) Kaycie the Catapillar (insects in food); (27:12) Judson Robinson visit to Baker College; (28:30) Pacifica Radio Station wins construction permit; (29:00) "Raid the Icebox" Andy Warhol exhibit; (29:48) Freshman football review Texas A and M; (30:32) Baker College pumpkin carving contest. Speakers: Buddy Trotter, Allen Matusow, Paul Pfeifer, Pat Baum, Bill Cavnar, Dick Fuqua, Bo Hagan, Julie Gianelloni, Dan Rather, Jack Olson, Bill Haymes, Jerry Jeff Walker
    - News Master C, 1969-11-03 - 1969-12-00; wrc07894 (Box 1)
      Contents include: (00:01) Timothy Leary at Southern Methodist University; (02:31) Intercollege Court ruling on Student Association elections; (05:31) Student Association Senate meeting review; (06:58) Student Association election voided; (09:49) Student Association Senate Vietnam Moratorium; (10:46) Bennett Falk re-instated; (11:26) Senate letter to University of Texas students about Frank Erwin; (12:35) Campanile in Life Magazine; (13:15) Review of Jones College's "The Prodigal"; (14:14) Coach Bo Hagan speaks about football; (15:21) Coach Bo Hagan at Wiess speech; (16:04) Campanile in Life Magazine; (17:01) Ted Farmer on Student Association Senate referendum; (17:58) CIA recruiters protest; (18:59) CIA recruiters protest; (20:20) Ted Farmer's referendum; (22:02) CIA recruiters protest update; (25:37) 2nd Vietnam Moratorium; (26:22) Vietnam Moratorium documentary promo; (27:32) Rice vs. Texas A and M football game review; (28:46) Ted Farmer interview on referendum; (29:53) Pep rally; (31:15) Brown Morality Play review; (32:06) Richard Neutra interview; (33:04) Ted Farmer off ballot; (34:40) Student comedy; (35:47) Commentary on draft lottery; (37:12) Intercollege Court election delayed; (38:02) School Board candidate Leonard Roberts interview; (39:36) Homemade newspaper bomb explosion; (40:27) Frank Vandiver's office on rumor of James Simms being next president; (41:15) Request for student on Board of Trustees and Intercollegiate Court proceedings; (42:15) Student Association Senate non meeting, absences; (43:09) Ted Melady interview on Rice Owls basketball; (44:02) Revolutionary Youth Movement films; (45:06) Rice Owls basketball vs Georgia Tech review. Speakers: Austin Bay, Pat Baum, Rick Weber, Bob Parks, Rod Crowl, Lee Horstman, Web Canard, Bennett Falk, Max Zimmerman, Scott Litin, Chip Matthews, John Doerr, Ted Farmer, Paul Levinka, Buddy Trotter, Chris Calvert, Frank Vandiver, Ben Tillison, Gary Maze, Leonard Roberts, Lee Horstman, Ted Melady, Paul Hlavinka
    - Program Master A, 1969/1970; wrc06207; 59017 (Box 1)
      Contents include: (00:01) Herman Professional Barbershop ad; (00:53) Gino's restaurant ad; (01:39) Dutch Kettle ad; (02:13) Smith and ZZ Top at the Houston Music Theater ad; (02:54:) Woody Allen's Take the Money and Run ad; (03:59) Easy Rider ad; (04:43) The Moody Blues at the Houston Music Theater ad; (05:38) Buger King ad; (06:20) The Jones Theater presents Dirty Work at the Crossroads; (06:54) Dromgoole's Typrewriter Shop ads; (08:55) Frank Vandiver's "Their Tattered Flags: The Epic of the Confederacy" ad; (10:07) Rice Campus Store ads; (11:45) Sammy's ads; (15:57) Graduation announcements at Rice Memorial Center ad; (16:35) Der Weinerschnitzel ads; (18:41) Denim at Golden Fleece Club ad; (19:41) Gino's restaurant ad; (20:14) Hamburgers by Gourmet ad; (24:10) American General Life Insurance ads; (30:47) Rice Campus Store ad; (31:31) Houston Symphony at Rice Field House ads. Speakers: Woody Allen, Smith, ZZ Top, The Moody Blues, Frank Vandiver, Fred Duckett
    - Program Master B, 1969/1970; wrc06208; 59018 (Box 1)
      Contents include: (00:01) Promo - Jim Gregory Show; (02:04) Promo - Jim Gregory Show; (03:20) Station ID - apology for bad signal; (04:11) Promo - Once Every Four Records; (05:03) Promo - Hit Line; (06:23) Station ID - The Big 58; (06:57) Station ID - Much More Music; (07:06) Station ID - Campus Information Station; (07:14) Station ID - 580 KTRU; (07:21) Station ID - Rice Owls; (07:29) Station ID - Much More Music; (07:38) Station ID - Lightnin' Hopkins; (07:46) Station ID - George Roy Hill; (07:58) Station ID - Big Band; (08:18) Station ID - Good Morning Sound; (08:34) Double Play; (08:42) New Music Now; (08:49) Three in a Row; (08:55) The Beat Goes On; (09:07) Station ID - Strikes Gold; (09:18) Golden Weekend; (09:24) Golden Classic; (09:33) More Music; (09:43) [?]; (09:52) Theme music; (10:03) Promo - KTRU News; (11:09) Promo - KTRU News Moratorium Day; (11:55) Promo - Mickey Swift; (13:50) Promo - Top 15 Artists; (14:25) Promo - Thomas Nast; (15:21) Promo - Jock-in-the-Box Contest; (16:44) Promo - [?] Norman Show; (17:17) Airing 3 hours April 1970 on KPFT 90.1 FM; (18:36) Theme music - Buddy Trotter and Music; (18:58) Theme music - Whole Rice Radio presents; (19:08) Theme music - Stinger. Speakers: Jim Gregory, Lightnin' Hopkins, George Roy Hill, Mickey Swift, Thomas Nast, Buddy Trotter, Herman Beiersdorf
    - Program Master C, 1969-00-00 - 1970-00-00; wrc06209; 59019 (Box 1)
      Contents include: (00:01) Win a date with Rob Quartel; (02:15) Carts introduction; (02:25) Wooo fx, (02:38) Aww now wait a minute; (02:47) electronic Star Spangled Banner; (03:10) Oh no; (03:16) Door, Door; (03:40) Weather; (03:46) Come on now; (03:55) KTRU promo by Rice Owls basketball player; (04:12) Horn flourish; (04:20) Apple gunkies; (04:34) Canned laughter; (04:45) Pouring soda in a glass; (04:57) Canned laughter; (05:04) Large audience canned laugher; (05:20) Cheering; (05:36) Mickey Swift promo; (05:48) KTRU promo; (05:58) Booing; (06:09) Superlatives; (06:23) KTRU promo; (06:39) KTRU show promo; (06:56) KTRU basketball team promo; (07:15) KTRU promo by basketball player; (07:45) gunshots/fireworks; (08:03) gong; (08:07) I don't get it; (08:13) You know it leads to harder stuff; (08:26) applause; (08:38) I never swinged it; (08:44) applause; (08:58) electronic signal; (09:17) Items crashing; (09:50) child speaking; (09:56) Chic and sophisticated; (10:03) That's a pretty car; (10:14) child speaking; (10:21) Steve Rogers promo; (11:33) Mickey Swift promo; (13:26) Library closure over Abbie Hoffman bomb threats; (14:34) Bill Wright; (14:41) So long; (15:35) KTRU promo; (16:05) KTRU promo; (16:30) KTRU Much More Music promo; (16:52) KTRU promo; (17:18) KTRU closed for repairs; (18:14) Scott Hill show intros; (18:40) Ron Harper show intros; (19:05) J. Leighton Read program intros; (19:25) Thomas Nast [?] program intros; (19:39) Jim Connor show intros; (20:03) Rob Quartel show intros: (20:28) Shawn Mackenzie [?] program intros; (20:52) Sid Marr [?] program intros; (21:17) Greg Reinhart show intros; (21:40) The Montgomery Show intros; (22:04) Greg Sporak show intros; (22:26) Jim Mead [?] show intros; (22:49) Jim Lawler show intros; (23:10) Rick Doyle [?] show intros; (23:32) Brad Etherton intros; (23:57) Jim McLaren show; (24:19) Dean Bradley [?] show intros; (24:29) Harvey Jay Spooner [?] show intros; (25:02) Steve Rogers show intros; (25:24) Buddy Trotter show intros; (27:01) Mickey Swift show intros; (27:24) Intro horn music; (28:30) Upbeat jazz music with drum solo; (31:52) Show intro. Speakers: Rob Quartel, Mickey Swift, Steve Rogers, Bill Wright, Scott Hill, Ron Harper, J. Leighton Read, Jim Connor, Greg Reinhart, Greg Sporak, Jim Lawler, Brad Etherton, Jim McLaren, Buddy Trotter
    - News Master D, Spring 1970; wrc06214; 59021 (Box 1)
      Contents include: (00:25) Super bowl commentary, Kansas City Chiefs; (01:23) Report on Afram and the British Empires response; (02:23) Review of Owlets basketball vs San Jacinto; (04:03) Art institute delay of opening of the media gallery; (04:47) Preview of Lamont Young and Marian Zazela environment "Dream House"; (06:07) Art Institute review preview of "Jules and Jim"; (06:55) Student Senate preview new constitution for SA; (07:58) Report from Houston school administration building on desegregation; (09:16) Report on Student Senate meeting 1970-01-20; (10:20) Report on Student Senate meeting; (12:05) Special report on campus security; (14:02) Review of "Dream House" exhibit; (15:58) "Riot on Campus" Hanszen film; (17:07) Report on upcoming Rice Owls football games; (18:55) Prediction on faculty vote strength on curriculum change proposal; (19:50) Stephen Baker commentary on curriculum change proposal; (20:32) Rice Owls Basketball preview; (21:38) Half-time Rice Owls vs. Texas A and M basketball game; (22:26) Preview of Student Senate meeting; (23:43) Review of Rice Owls vs. Texas A and M basketball game; (24:46) Anti-G.E. rally; (25:25) Interview on co-ed dorm possibility; (26:49) Rice Owlettes vs. Texas A and M basketball summary and preview; (29:05) Report on co-educational dorm proposal; (30:31) Report on the anti-G.E. rally; (33:06) Interview with Matt Harris on Anti-G.E. rally; (35:58) Curriculum reform news promo; (36:58) Review of Lightnin' Hopkins concert at Jewish Community Center; (38:08) RAC protest of ROTC recruiting; (39:08) Opinion on President Nixon's anti-crime bill; (40:10) Interim President Frank Vandiver on proposed third women's college; (41:18) Review of Jones College melodrama; (42:43) The Band coming to Houston; (43:58) Preview of Rice Owls vs. Baylor Bears basketball game. Speakers: Pat Baum, Miriam Wilcox, Gary Mayes, John Doerr, Paul Muncy, Julie Gianelloni, George Greanias, Stephen Baker, Doyon Main, Bill Katzenberg, George Greanias, Jack Reeves, Matt Harris, Chip Matthews, Kerry Vandell, Christine Ehlig, Frank Vandiver
    - News Master E, 1970-02-00 - 1970-02-16; wrc07895 (Box 1)